i want you to check this out right this
is the entire old testament
we are juicing this thing down guys if
you look at the books of
genesis to judges we just covered
wow that parallels the story of jesus
the second adam
uh who comes to die for our sins as our
passover
who sets up a heavenly sanctuary and
becomes our heavenly high priest
that would cover the 70-week prophecy
christ's first coming
his inauguration as our high priest
when we get to the book of first samuel
all the way up to the captivity
this is basically paralleling the 1260
year prophecy
in which there is apostasy the sanctuary
is defiled and a
power name babylon is dominating god's
people
and what are the last events of the old
testament
they are chronicled in the books of ezra
nehemiah
and esther these three minor prophets
haggai zechariah and malachi parallel
that time
but it's all around the time of the
rebuilding of the temple
and the city and that is the context
of the book of esther are you
with me so far let's now go
to the book of esther and we are now
about to break down the book of esther
and you're about to see stuff that
you're going to be like oh wow
because remember now esther
is given within the context of the books
of ezra and nehemiah
the rebuilding of the sanctuary the
restoration of a sanctuary which we have
just seen
is in the context of the 2300
day prophecy the entire old testament is
broken down
into this into these three sections 70
weeks paralleling
1260 paralleling 2300 paralleling
and then the first coming of jesus so
watch this
the book of ezra ezra chapter one
the bible says now it came to pass in
the days of azeroth that is azir's which
reigned from india even unto ethiopia
over a hundred and seven and twenty
provinces that in those days
when the king aceros sat on the throne
of his kingdom which was in shusham the
palace
that's very interesting that is
really really very interesting that the
book of esther begins with this
king who is sitting on his throne
in his kingdom
i need you all to catch this very
carefully guys
notice what it goes on to say in the
third year of his reign he made a
feast onto all his princes and his
servants
the power of the persia and media and
the power of persia and media the nobles
and princes of the provinces being
before him
so everyone is gathered before this king
who is seated on his throne
now i know what you're saying right now
pastor that's just coincidence
hold your thought hold your thumb
because we're going to see something
just keep following me because you know
that in daniel 7 verse
9 it is significant that the bible
describes
the king of kings the bible describes
god i beheld till thrones were cast down
and the
ancient of days did sit whose garment
was white as snow
and the hair of his head like pure wool
his throne was like the fiery flame and
his wheels is burning fire let me
give you a little bit of context here
remember this
esther the story of esther
is occurring after the children of
israel have
left to begin rebuilding the temple
so they're still they didn't leave for
some people some of the jews did not
leave to go rebuild the temple
so this is happening in the middle
persian
empire okay people
god's people who were still in the
middle persian
empire and and i want you to check this
out so this is kind of like
they're under a secular if you will
society
right they're not in in jerusalem where
where
they're able to do the things that they
would do as jews so watch this
esther one verse five the bible says and
when these days were
expired the king made a feast onto all
the people that were present in shushan
please remember that name shushan please
remember that place
in shushan the palace both onto great
and small
even seven days in the court of the
garden
of the king's palace where were white
green and blue
hangings fastened with cords of fine
linen
and purple to silver rings and the
pillars of the marble
that the beds were of gold and silver
upon a pavement of red blue
white black and marble does any of this
sound sanctuary ish to you
i just want you to catch the illusions
to the sanctuary you have a king sitting
on his throne
you have these these curtains and fine
linen
and and remember we're dealing with a
secular king right we're dealing with a
secular society
but please pay careful attention to this
so come on let's keep going and all the
king's servants that were in the king's
gate bowed and reverenced haman
for the king had so commanded concerning
him but mordecai
bowed not nor did him reverend so in
this story you'll remember
that haman is exalted to this high
position and so
everyone is bound to haman except
mordecai
he refuses to bother him and as a result
the bible says the king's servants which
are in the king's gate said unto
mordecai
why transgressive thou the king's
commandment and this is how this whole
thing starts because
uh a haman is angry that mordecai
will not bow to him
so the bible says it came to pass when
they speak daily unto him
and he hearken not unto them that they
told haman to see whether mordecai's
matter would stand
for he had told them that he was a jew
and when haman saw that mordecai bowed
not
nor did him reverence then was haman
full of wrath now pause for a second
let me ask you a question do you think
satan would like you to bow to him
come on guys satan is walking up and
down in this world claiming it as his
own
do you think satan would like you to bow
to him
obviously the answer is yes so when you
don't bow to satan
when you don't give in to satan when you
don't you know
like coward before satan when you say
satan i'm not following you i'm not
bowing down before you
do you think that gets satan full of
wrath what do you think yes or no
yeah i think that gets satan full of
wrath i think that gets satan pretty
angry
so notice what happens the bible says
and he thought to scorn to lay hands
so i want you to remember this term guys
he thought it was going to
lay hands on mordecai alone for they had
sold him the people of mordecai
wherefore haman sought to destroy all
the jews that were throughout the whole
kingdom of azerus
even the people of mordecai in the first
first month that is the month of nisan
in the twelfth year of king ahasuras
they cast per that is the lot
before haman from day to day and from
month to month
to the 12th month that is the month of
adar so they're casting lots and the
bible says
haman said unto king hazaris there's a
certain people scattered abroad
and dispersed among the people and all
the prophecies of thy kingdom
and their laws are diverse from all
people
neither keep they the king's laws
therefore it is not for the king's
prophet to suffer them
so in other words let me break that down
whatever this process of casting lots
was
they were basically haman was choosing
was deciding when the jews should be
destroyed
that's that was the purpose of casting
these lots to destroy the jews
so verse 9 says if it please the king
let it be written
that they may be destroyed and i will
pay 10 000 talents of silver
to the hands of those that have the
charge of the business to bring it into
the king's treasures
you get the idea here right i want you
to check this out revelation 12 17 says
the dragon was
wrath with the woman and went to make
war with the remnant of her seed which
keep the commandments of god and have
the testimony of jesus
i need you to see this here beloved that
haman in this story
is a type of satan himself
he is angry when we don't bow he is
angry because we are keeping the
commandments of god now remember beloved
we are studying this in the context of
where
esther is found in the history of the
old testament
genesis to judges you got the setting of
the sanctuary the setting up of the
priesthood
first samuel to chronicles you have
apostasy you have
babylon ruling you have the temple being
defiled and then
ezra nehemiah and esther you have the
temple being rebuilt
the sanctuary being rebuilt and restored
and
in the midst of that this story of
esther haman is casting
lots to destroy the people of god
he is angry because they are keeping the
commandments
they're not keeping the laws of this
world they're keeping the commandments
of god and satan
is angry he wants to destroy
the people of god so notice what it goes
on to say
verse 13 and letters were sent by posts
and all the king's prophecies to destroy
to kill
and to cause to perish all jews both
young and old
little children and women and in one day
even upon the 13th day of the 12th month
which is the month of adar
and to take the spoil of them for
praying the copy of the writing for a
commandment to be given and every
province was published unto all the
people
that they should be ready against the
day in other words there was
a in a sense a universal decree
to attempt to wipe out the people of god
that reminds me of revelation chapter 13
verse 15
that says and he had power to give life
unto the image of the beast
that the image of the beast should both
speak and cause that as many as would
not
worship the image of the beast should be
killed very interesting parallels here
we know that this is what will happen in
the end of time we know that this is
what will happen
in the context of the 2300 day prophecy
but i want to show you something very
specific here
notice notice what happens right so
mordecai
uh knows about this decree and so he
sends
message to esther who has become
the king's wife she has become the
king's wife
and the bible says all the king's
servants so this is esther's response
when she hears what's going on she sends
response to mordecai
she says all the king's servants and the
people of the king's province do know
that whosoever whether man or woman
shout
i got a pause right here i gotta pause
right here
whosoever whether man or woman shall
come
unto the king into the inner court
for some reason this inner court is off
limits
you cannot enter it uninvited
i need y'all to catch this man i need
you all to see
this story of esther in the context of
where it is placed
in old testament history
esther knows that she cannot enter into
a place
listen there is one law of his to put
him to
death except such to whom the king shall
hold out the golden scepter that he may
live
but i have not been called to come into
the king these 30 days
and they told to mordecai mordecai
esther's words
then mordecai commanded to answer esther
fit not
with thyself that thou shalt escape in
the king's house
more than all the jews for if thou
altogether hold
thy peace at this time if you are not
doing something at this time then shall
be in their enlargement and deliverance
arise to the jews from another place
but thou when thy father house shall be
destroyed and who knows
whether thou art come to the kingdom for
such a time
as 1844 i mean for such a time
as this
who knows whether you have been brought
upon the scene
church bride of christ
for such a time as this to intercede
to to plead to to witness
to share the gospel with a people who
satan is about to try to destroy
then estimate them return mordechai this
answer go
gather together all the jews that are
present in shushan remember that place
shushan and fast for me
and neither eat nor drink three days nor
night or day
i also and my maidens will fast likewise
and so will i go
in unto the king into that you know that
most
sacred place of this king i will go into
the king which is not according to the
law
if i perish i perish there is there is
trepidation here i
know what the investigative judgment can
sound like it can sound like something
scary
sound like something that is just like
man can we even
stand in the presence of the king but
beloved i'm here to tell you today
that god has the best intentions for you
in this investigative judgment do not be
afraid
we have been brought to the kingdom for
such
a time as this below